Soumyabrata DEV

Contact Information The ADAPT Centre

Room G31, O'Reilly Building Dublin 2, Trinity College Dublin

Ireland

Executive Statement

I am a researcher with interests in image processing, machine learning, and deep learning. Most specifically, I use these expertise in solving problems related to consumer digital media, remote sensing, earth sciences, solar and renewable energy.

Current Affiliation

University College Dublin, Ireland

August 2019 – till date

soumyabrata.dev@adaptcentre.ie

https://soumyabrata.dev/

Assistant Professor in Computer Science

- Leading our research group THEIA: THE visIon and Analytics lab, in the area of computer vision, image processing, and remote sensing.
- Teaching courses in distributed systems, network security, and agile methodology.

Education

Nanyang Technological University (NTU) Singapore

2012 - 2017

Ph.D. in Electrical & Electronic Engineering

Thesis: 2D and 3D Image Analysis and Its Application to Sky/Cloud Imaging

CGPA: 4.08/5.0

National Institute of Technology Silchar, India

2006 - 2010

Bachelor of Technology in Electronics & Communication Engineering

Graduated summa cum laude with highest honors and ranked 1 in class of 70

CGPA: 9.43/10.0

Experience

ADAPT Centre, Trinity College Dublin

July 2017 - July 2019

Postdoctoral Researcher

Worked with Prof. François Pitié and Declan McKibben, in industry-affiliated research projects of Huawei Ireland Research Centre.

- Developed state-of-the-art techniques for effective image- and video- analysis in consumer advertisement videos.
- Published our findings in leading conferences.

National College of Ireland, Dublin

August 2018 – August 2019

Associate Faculty in Computing

- Lectured courses in programming and data analytics.
- Supervised students for their Master of Science research projects.

Nanyang Technological University Singapore PhD Student

Singapore, Singapore July 2012 – July 2017

Worked with Prof. Lee Yee Hui, NTU Singapore and Dr. Stefan Winkler, Principal Scientist, Advanced Digital Sciences Center (ADSC).

- Developed state-of-the-art image segmentation and image classification algorithms for cloud image analysis and earth observations.
- Created and released first large-scale cloud image datasets with manually annotated labels to the community.
- Published our findings in top-tier journals and conferences.

École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne

Lausanne, Switzerland July 2015 – December 2015

Visiting Student July 2015 – December 20 Worked with Prof. Martin Vetterli and Dr. Adam Scholefield during this exchange term.

- Devised algorithms with theoretical bounds for point localization in multi-camera setups with noisy camera poses.
- Provided a rigorous analysis of such localization problems in the task of cloud-base height reconstruction using ground-based sky cameras.

Ericsson India Gurgaon, India

Engineer - Network Consulting

July 2010 – July 2012

- Provided 2G frequency planning and optimization for metropolitan cities, and received excellent customer feedback.
- Developed heuristic processes and optimization techniques to streamline the 2G/3G network operations. Developed tool was subsequently included into Ericsson's tools and services portal.

Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore

Bangalore, India

Research Intern

May 2009 – July 2009

Worked with Prof. Vinod Sharma during this internship period.

- Developed a high performance source-relay assignment scheme, denoted Timer based Adaptive Relay Selection Protocol (TARSeP) that efficiently improves the overall throughput in wireless 802.11 networks.
- Published our results in a journal of related area.

Indian Institute of Technology Guwahati

Guwahati, India

Research Intern

May 2008 – June 2008

Worked with Prof. Harshal B. Nemade during this internship period.

- Designed a minimum off-time device for protecting refrigerator compressor after a brief power interruption.
- Developed a working prototype of the designed device using off-the-shelf components.

Teaching

National College of Ireland

Dublin

Associate Faculty

July 2018 – August 2019

- Lectured a course on 'Programming for big data' for Higher Diploma in Science in Data Analytics for the term January 2019 May 2019.
- Lectured a course on H9PDA: Programming for Data Analytics, for degree in Masters in Cloud Computing for the term August 2018 December 2018, and June 2019 August 2019.

Trinity College Dublin, Ireland

Dublin

Teaching Assistant

January 2019 - till date

- Currently conducting the lab sessions of EEU44C08 Digital Image and Video Processing, for fourth year undergraduates of Trinity College Dublin, for the term January 2019 – May 2019.

NTU Singapore Outreach Team

Singapore

Instructor

January 2015 – June 2017

- Reached out to pre-tertiary students with a passion for Science and Engineering, and received commendable appreciation from Ministry of Education, Singapore.
- Developed learning programmes (viz. Cantenna workshop & LED Cube workshop) that offered students an opportunity to appreciate STEM field education, under the tutelage of NTU professors and staffs.

NTU Singapore Undergraduate Class

Singapore

Peer Tutor

2016 - 2017

Teaching Assistant

2014 - 2016

- Taught the course EE2008: Data Structures and Algorithms to 150+ students for Semester 1 AY 2014–15, and Semester 2 AY 2015-16 session.
- Received Best Teaching Award for the course.

Supervision

National College of Ireland

Dublin

Supervisor

July 2018 - till date

- Supervised 3 students in their Master of Science (MSc) research thesis, in areas of machine learning and data analytics.

Nanyang Technological University Singapore

Singapore

Mentor

January 2013 – June 2017

- Mentored 14 students in their Final Year Projects (FYPs) and Nanyang Research Program (NRP) projects, in areas of image processing and remote sensing.

- Invited Talks Invited talk at the IEEE YP Symposium on Impact of Data Science in Healthcare, Dublin, July 2019.
 - Invited talk at Machine Learning Dublin meetup to discuss our recent work on deeplearning based advert-creation system, developed in collaboration with Huawei Ireland Research Centre, June 2019.
 - Talk on the course 'Inside the Machine: An Introduction to Architecture, Parallelism & its Applications', at University College Dublin, Dublin, Ireland, May 2019.
 - Undergraduate research talk on 'Solving Interdisciplinary Problems Using Computer Vision', at Maynooth University, Co. Kildare, February 2019.
 - Research talk on 'Computer-Vision Solutions for Sensing Problems', at University of Dundee, Scotland, October 2018.
 - Talk on the course 'Inside the Machine: An Introduction to Architecture, Parallelism & Electronics', at Bucknell University, Lewisburg, PA, United States, July 2018.
 - Seminar on 'Developing Computer-Vision Solutions for Sensing Problems in Intelligent Systems', at University of Derby, United Kingdom, April 2018.
 - Talk on 'Ground-based Image Analysis for Solar Energy Applications' in Machine Learning Dublin meetup at The Innovation Academy TCD, August 2017.

Publications

2019

- S. Manandhar, S. Dev, Y. H. Lee, Y. S. Meng, and S. Winkler, A Data-Driven Approach for Accurate Rainfall Prediction, IEEE Transactions on Geoscience and Remote Sensing, 2019.
- F. Orlandi, A. Meehan, M. Hossari, S. Dev, D. O'Sullivan and T. Alskaif, Interlinking Heterogeneous Data for Smart Energy Systems, International Conference on Smart Energy Systems and Technologies (SEST), 2019.
- S. Dev, M. Hossari, M. Nicholson, K. McCabe, A. Nautiyal, C. Conran, J. Tang, W. Xu, and F. Pitié, Localizing Adverts in Outdoor Scenes, IEEE International Conference on Multimedia & Expo Workshops (ICMEW), 2019.
- S. Dev, M. Hossari, M. Nicholson, K. McCabe, A. Nautiyal, C. Conran, J. Tang, W. Xu, and F. Pitié, The ALOS Dataset for Advert Localization in Outdoor Scenes, Eleventh International Conference on Quality of Multimedia Experience (QoMEX), 2019.
- C. S. Nwosu(⋆), S. Dev(⋆), P. Bhardwaj, B. Veeravalli, and C. J. Deepu, Understanding Electronic Health Records for Stroke Prediction, 41st Annual International Conference of the IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society (EMBC), 2019 (* Authors contributed equally).

- T. AlSkaif(*), S. Dev(*), L. Visser, M. Hossari, and W. van Sark, On the Interdependence and Importance of Meteorological Variables for Photovoltaic Output Power Estimation, 46th IEEE Photovoltaic Specialists Conference (PVSC), 2019 (* Authors contributed equally).
- S. Dev, A. Nautiyal, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, CloudSegNet: A Deep Network for Nychthemeron Cloud Segmentation, *IEEE Geoscience and Remote Sensing Letters*, 2019.
- S. Dev, M. Hossari, M. Nicholson, K. McCabe, A. Nautiyal, C. Conran, J. Tang, W. Xu, and F. Pitié, The CASE Dataset of Candidate Spaces for Advert Implantation, *International Conference on Machine Vision Applications (MVA)*, 2019.
- S. Dev, S. Manandhar, Y. H. Lee and S. Winkler, Multi-label Cloud Segmentation Using a Deep Network, *IEEE AP-S Symposium on Antennas and Propagation and USNC-URSI Radio Science Meeting*, 2019.
- S. Manandhar(*), S. Dev(*), Y. H. Lee and S. Winkler, Predicting GPS-based PWV Measurements Using Exponential Smoothing, *IEEE AP-S Symposium on Antennas and Propagation and USNC-URSI Radio Science Meeting*, 2019 (* Authors contributed equally).
- M. Hossari, S. Dev and J. D. Kelleher, TEST: A Terminology Extraction System for Technology Related Terms, 11th International Conference on Computer and Automation Engineering (ICCAE), 2019.

2018

- M. Hossari(*), S. Dev(*), M. Nicholson, K. McCabe, A. Nautiyal, C. Conran, J. Tang, W. Xu, and F. Pitié, ADNet: A Deep Network for Detecting Adverts, 26th Irish Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Cognitive Science (AICS), 2018 (* Authors contributed equally and arranged alphabetically.).
- A. Nautiyal(*), K. McCabe(*), M. Hossari(*), S. Dev(*), M. Nicholson, C. Conran, D. McKibben, J. Tang, X. Wei, and F. Pitié, An Advert Creation System for Next-Gen Publicity, European Conference on Machine Learning and Principles and Practice of Knowledge Discovery in Databases (ECM-PKDD), 2018 (* Authors contributed equally and arranged alphabetically.).
- S. Dev(*), T. AlSkaif(*), M. Hossari, R. Godina, A. Louwen, and W. van Sark, Solar Irradiance Forecasting Using Triple Exponential Smoothing, *International Conference on Smart Energy Systems and Technologies (SEST)*, 2018 (* Authors contributed equally).
- S. Manandhar(*), S. Dev(*), Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler and Y. S. Meng, Systematic Study
 of Weather Variables for Rainfall Detection, *IEEE International Geoscience and Remote*Sensing Symposium (IGARSS), 2018 (* Authors contributed equally).
- S. Manandhar, S. Dev, Y. H. Lee, Y. S. Meng and S. Winkler, A Data-driven Approach to Detect Precipitation from Meteorological Sensor Data, *IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS)*, 2018.
- F. Pitié, A. Nautiyal, S. Dev, M. Nicholsan, A. Abdelkader, K. McCabe, C. Conran, D. McKibben, An automatic system that identifies and locates the four corners of the advertising space in a video as a cloud service, *Patent Filed*, 2018.
- F. Pitié, A. Nautiyal, S. Dev, M. Nicholsan, A. Abdelkader, K. McCabe, C. Conran, D. McKibben, An algorithm that ranks candidate advertising spaces based on their quality and value, *Patent Filed*, 2018.
- S. Manandhar, Y. H. Lee, Y. S. Meng, F. Yuan and S. Dev, A Potential Low Cost Remote Sensing Using GPS Derived PWV, *IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing* Symposium (IGARSS), 2018.
- S. Dev, F. M. Savoy, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, High-Dynamic-Range Imaging for Cloud Segmentation, *Atmospheric Measurement Techniques (AMT)*, 2018.
- S. Manandhar(⋆), S. Dev(⋆), Y. H. Lee and Y. S. Meng, Analyzing Solar Irradiance Variation From GPS and Cameras, IEEE AP-S Symposium on Antennas and Propagation and USNC-URSI Radio Science Meeting, 2018 (⋆ Authors contributed equally).

• S. Manandhar, S. Dev, Y. H. Lee and Y. S. Meng, On the Importance of PWV in Detecting Precipitation, *IEEE AP-S Symposium on Antennas and Propagation and USNC-URSI Radio Science Meeting*, 2018.

2017

- S. Dev, F. M. Savoy, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, Rough-set Based Visible Color Channel Selection, *IEEE Geoscience and Remote Sensing Letters*, vol. 14, no. 1, pp. 52-56, 2017.
- S. Dev, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, Color-based segmentation of sky/cloud images from ground-based cameras, *IEEE Journal of Selected Topics in Applied Earth Observations and Remote Sensing*, vol. 10, no. 1, pp. 231-242, Jan 2017.
- S. Dev, F. M. Savoy, Y. H. Lee and S. Winkler, DIY Sky Imager For Weather Observation: A complete guide to build a ground-based sky imager using off-the-shelf components with automatic cloud coverage computation, Students' Design Project Series: Sharing Experiences [SP Education], IEEE Signal Processing Magazine, Jan 2017.
- S. Dev, S. Manandhar, Y. H. Lee and S. Winkler, Study of Clear Sky Models for Singapore, Proc. Progress In Electromagnetics Research Symposium (PIERS), 2017.
- S. Manandhar, S. Dev, Y. H. Lee and Y. S. Meng, Analyzing Cloud Optical Properties Using Sky Cameras, Proc. Progress In Electromagnetics Research Symposium (PIERS), 2017.
- S. Manandhar, S. Dev, Y. H. Lee and Y. S. Meng, Correlating Satellite Cloud Cover with Sky Cameras, *Proc. Progress In Electromagnetics Research Symposium (PIERS)*, 2017.
- S. Dev, F. Savoy, Y. H. Lee and S. Winkler, Nighttime sky/cloud image segmentation, *IEEE International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP)*, 2017.
- F. Savoy, S. Dev, Y. H. Lee and S. Winkler, Stereoscopic Cloud Base Reconstruction Using High-Resolution Whole Sky Imagers, *IEEE International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP)*, 2017.
- S. Dev, S. Manandhar, F. Yuan, Y. H. Lee and S. Winkler, Cloud Radiative Effect Study Using Sky Camera, IEEE AP-S Symposium on Antennas and Propagation and USNC-URSI Radio Science Meeting, 2017.

2016

- S. Dev, B. Wen, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, Machine Learning Techniques and Applications For Ground-based Image Analysis, *IEEE Geoscience and Remote Sensing Magazine, Special Issue on Advances in Machine Learning for Remote Sensing and Geosciences*, vol. 4, no. 2, pp. 79-93, June 2016.
- S. Dev, S. Manandhar, Y. H. Lee and S. Winkler, Detecting rainfall onset using sky images, TENCON 2016 - 2016 IEEE Region 10 Conference, 2016.
- S. Dev, F. M. Savoy, Y. H. Lee and S. Winkler, Short-term prediction of localized cloud motion using ground-based sky imagers, TENCON 2016 - 2016 IEEE Region 10 Conference, 2016.
- S. Manandhar, F. Yuan, S. Dev, Y. H. Lee and Y. S. Meng, Weather radar to detect cloud occurrence level, TENCON 2016 2016 IEEE Region 10 Conference, 2016.
- S. Dev, F. M. Savoy, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, Estimation of solar irradiance using ground-based whole sky imagers, *IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS)*, 2016.
- F. M. Savoy, S. Dev, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, Geo-referencing and stereo calibration of ground-based whole sky imagers using the sun trajectory, *IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS)*, 2016.
- S. Manandhar, Y. H. Lee, S. Dev, GPS Derived PWV for rainfall monitoring, *IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS)*, 2016.

2015

- S. Dev, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, Categorization of Cloud Image Patches Using an Improved Texton-based Approach, *IEEE International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP)*, 2015.
- S. Dev, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, Multi-level Semantic Labeling of sky/cloud images, *IEEE International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP)*, 2015.
- S. Dev, F. M. Savoy, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, Design of low-cost, compact and weather-proof whole sky imagers for high-dynamic-range captures, *IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS)*, 2015.
- F. M. Savoy, S. Dev, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, Cloud base height estimation using high-resolution whole sky imagers, *IEEE International Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS)*, 2015.
- S. Dev, A. Ghasemi, M. Vetterli, A. Scholefield, Point localization in Multi-camera system, Doctoral internship report, École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne, Switzerland, 2015.

2014

- S. Dev, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, Systematic Study of Color Spaces and Components for the segmentation of sky/cloud images, *IEEE International Conference on Image Processing (ICIP)*, 2014.
- S. Dev, F. M. Savoy, Y. H. Lee, S. Winkler, WAHRSIS: A low-cost, high-resolution whole sky imager with near-infrared capabilities, *Proc. IS&T/SPIE Infrared Imaging Systems: Design, Analysis, Modeling, and Testing*, 2014.

2010

• S. Dev, Z.H. Choudhury, K. L. Baishnab, A. Nag, An efficient heap management technique with Minimum Fragmentation and Auto Compaction, *IEEE International Conference on Industrial and Information Systems*, 2010.

2009

- S. Dev, Nischal S, An efficient partner assignment algorithm for improving the performance of 802.11 WLAN, *International Journal of Recent Trends in Engineering*, vol. 2, no. 6, Nov. 2009, Issue on Electrical and Electronics.
- S. Dev, Z. H. Choudhury, A randomized cryptographic algorithm and its simulation in C and MATLAB, with its hardware implementation in Verilog HDL, *IEEE Conference on Anti-Counterfeiting, Security and Identification*, Aug 2009.

Skills Languages

Python, MATLAB, Perl.

Technologies

TensorFlow, Keras, LATEX

Expertise

image processing, machine learning, remote sensing, deep learning.

Media Links

- Github: github.com/Soumyabrata
- Publons: publons.com/author/1307481/soumyabrata-dev
- Google Scholar: scholar.google.com.sg/citations?user=_akXw8IAAAAJ

Organization Xonkolpo

North-East India

Advisor

October 2013 – present

- Assisted in floating Xonkolpo: a non-profit initiative, along with other enthusiasts from Assam, India.

- Provided support and guidance, along with application materials for students, particularly from North-Eastern India to pursue studies in any Science, Technology, Engineering and Management (STEM) field.

NTU - Graduate Student Council

Singapore

Director April 2016 – March 2017
Director April 2015 – March 2016
Public Relations Officer May 2014 – March 2015

- Lead NTUGSC - Career & Entrepreneurship committee that is primarily involved in organizing Career talks, Entrepreneurial talks and Industrial visits for the graduate students.

- Established long-term collaborations with NTU - Career & Attachment Office (CAO) for our activities.

IEEE Young Professionals

Singapore

Chair November 2015 – November 2016
Vice Chair November 2014 – November 2014
Executive Committee Member November 2013 – October 2014

- Lead the Singapore chapter of IEEE Young Professionals, and was primarily involved in facilitating young graduates to become world class professionals, enhancing their skills and establishing a strong and diverse professional network.

- Received best Affinity Group award from IEEE R10 section.

IEEE Student Chapter Silchar

Silchar, India

Executive Committee Member June 2008 – June 2010

- Responsible for the overall management of IEEE Student Chapter Branch affairs.

Awards & Honors

- Awarded the Outstanding Academic Achievement award, by Technology Ireland, November 2018.
- Awarded the ADAPT Centre Directors Commercialisation Award 2018, in recognition of the contribution to Huawei Advert project.
- Recognition and appreciation for contribution as a tutor in the Peer Tutoring Scheme, NTU Singapore, AY 2016-17.
- IEEE Region-10 Young Professionals Affinity Group Award in recognition and appreciation of valued services and contributions, August 2016.
- Commendable Teaching Assistant Award for the AY 2014–15 by School of Electrical and Electronic Engineering, NTU Singapore, November 2015.
- Institute Silver Medal in Bachelor of Technology, National Institute of Technology Silchar, July 2010.

References

Available on request.